Finding Aid for Carl Cohen papers, 1950-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Publications
  - Published Articles
    - "Sex, Birth Control, and Human Life" Ethics, Vol. 79, No. 4, July 1969 (Box 61)
      (article #89)
    - "Which Way is Left?" The Yale Law Review, Vol. 58, No. 4, Summer 1969 (Box 61)
      (article 90)
    - "Democracy and the Curriculum" The Nation, Vol. 208, No. 11, March 17, 1969 (Box 61)
      (article #91)
    - "Democracy and the Curriculum" Michigan Quarterly Review, Vol. VIII, No. 3, July, 1969 (Box 61)
      (article #91a)
    - About Letters The Nation, May 12, 1969 (Box 61)
      (article #91b)
    - "Civil Disobedience: Moral or Not?" The Nation, Vol. 207, No. 19, December 2, 1968 (Box 61)
      (article #92)
    - "Conscientious Objection" Ethics, Vol. 78, No. 4, July 1968 (Box 61)
      (article #93)
    - "The Case for Selective Pacifism" The Nation, Vol. 207, No. 1, July 8, 1968 (Box 61)
      (article #94)
    - "Civil Disobedience and the Law" Rutgers Law Review, Vol. 21, No. 1, Fall 1966 (Box 61)
      (article #95)
    - "Law, Speech, and Disobedience" The Nation, Vol. 201, No. 22, December 27, 1965 (Box 61)
      (article #96)
    - "Punishment by Conscription" The Nation, Vol. 201, No. 22, December 27, 1965 (Box 61)
      (article #97)
    - The Nation, January 3, 1966 (Box 61)
      (article #97a)
    - "The Poverty of a Dialogue" Problems of Communism, Vol. XIII, September-October 1964 (Box 61)
      (article #98)
    - "The Ethics of Civil Disobedience" The Nation, Vol. 198, No. 12, March 16, 1964 (Box 61)
      (article #99)
    - "Democracy and Its Economic Conditions" Proceedings, Thirteenth International Congress of Philosophy, Mexico City, 1963 (Box 61)
      (article 100)
    - "Some Implications of Control" Biological Influents in Mental Health Michigan Department of Mental Health, 1962 (Box 61)
      (article 101)
    - "Criminal Responsibility and the Knowledge of Right and Wrong" University of Miami Law Review, Vol. 14, No. 1, Fall 1959 (Box 61)
      (article 102)
    - "Natural and Non-Natural Qualities" The Journal of Philosophy, Vol. 55, No. 10, May 8, 1958 (Box 61)
      (article 103)
    - "Naturalism and the Method of Verstehen" The Journal of Philosophy, Vol. 51, No. 7, April 1, 1954 (Box 61)
      (article #104)
  - Published Review Articles
    - "Perversion of the Hail Mary Pass" Review of Diversity in America, by Peter H. Schuck, Harvard University Press, 2003. In The Times Higher Education Supplement, London, February 13, 2004 (Box 61)
      (article #105 missing)
    - "Groupthink" A review of Affirmative Action around the World, by Thomas Sowell, published in Commentary, April 2004, Volume 117, No. 4 (Box 61)
      (article #106)
    - "Against Liberalism" a review of the book of the same name, by John Kekes, Cornell University Press, 1997 published in International Studies in Philosophy, January 2004 (Box 61)
      (article #107 missing)
    - "Fears of Human Cloning are Without Merit" a review of Clone: The Road to Dolly and the Path Ahead, by Gina Kolata, The Detroit News, 1998 (Box 61)
      (article 108 missing)
    - "The Tension between Equality and Autonomy," a review of Against Liberalism, by John Kekes, in International Studies in Philosophy, Autumn 1997 (Box 61)
      (article 109 missing)
    - "Aristocrat, Saint, Capitalist, Socialist" Review of The Great Alternatives of Social Thought, Terrence E. Cook, in Ethics, January, 1993 (Box 61)
      (article 110 missing)
    - "The Reverse Discrimination Controversy" International Studies in Philosophy, Vol. XIV, No. 2, 1981 (Box 61)
      (article 111 missing)
    - "What is 'Affirmative Action'?" Texas Law Review, Vol. 58, No. 4, April 1980 (Box 61)
      (article 112)
    - "Justice and Reverse Discrimination " International Studies in Philosophy, Vol. XII, No. 1, 1980 (Box 61)
      (article #113 missing)
    - "Ethnic Justice, Individual Rights" The Chronicle of Higher Education, Vol. XII, No. 1, March 1, 1976 (Box 61)
      (article #114 missing)
    - "On Keeping One's Balance" Review of The Balancing Act: Quota Hiring in Higher Education, by George Roche. In Michigan Academician, Vol. VIII, No. 3, Winter 1976 (Box 61)
      (article #115)
    - "The Ideal of the University" Review of book of the same name, by Robert P. Wolff. Michigan Quarterly Review, Vol. X, No. 4, Fall 1971 (Box 61)
      (article #116)
    - "Superman and Common Men" Review of book of the same name, by Benjamin Barber College Review Service, Blue Mounds, Wisconsin (Box 61)
      (article #117)
    - "The Potency of Truth, the Power of Love" Review of Black Freedom: The Nonviolent Abolitionists from 1830 Through the Civil War, by Carleton Mabee. The Nation, Vol. 210, No. 17, May 4, 1970 (Box 61)
      (article #118)
    - "Democracy and the University" Review of Up Against the Ivy Wall: A History of the Columbia Crisis, by Jerry L. Avorn, et al. The Yale Review, Vol. 58, No. 3, Spring 1969 (Box 61)
      (article #119)
    - Review of Political Authority and Moral Judgment, by G. Negley. The Philosophical Review, Vol. 76, No. 2, April 1967 (Box 61)
      (article #120 missing)
    - Review of Discrimination and Reverse Discrimination, by K. Greenawalt. Law and Philosophy, Vol. 5, no. 3 (Box 61)
      (article #121; see #46)
    - "John Dewey, The League of Nations, and War" in the Proceedings of the Association for the Philosophy of Education, Winter, 1985-1986 (Box 61)
      (article #122 missing)
  - Published and / or articles with preliminary titles
    (titles lacking from numbered sequence, arranged chronologically)
    - Undated 1952-2012, 44 folders (Box 62)
  - Lectures/Speeches
    - Against Proposed Graduation Requirements on Diversity 1990 (Box 62)
    - Arbitrating Labor/Management Conflicts: Philosophical Reflections 1987 (Box 62)
    - Can Democracy Work? (Box 62)
    - Capital Punishment (Box 62)
    - Compensatory Justice (Box 62)
    - Defense of Democracy (Box 62)
    - Democracy, 2 folders (Box 62)
    - Democracy at the University (Box 62)
    - Ewing case review 1986 (Box 62)
    - Freedom of Speech (Box 62)
    - Freedom to be Bad (Box 62)
    - Human Nature and Moral Educating 1983 (Box 62)
    - Individual Rights and the Common Good (Box 62)
    - The Limits of Free Speech 1983 (Box 62)
    - Machiavelli Revisited (Box 62)
    - On Civil Disobedience (Box 62)
    - On Defending Freedom of Speech (Box 62)
    - On the Practicality of Theory 1987 (Box 62)
    - Phi Chi Notes for Sale! (Box 62)
    - Philosophical underpinnings of the American Revolution (Box 62)
    - Reflections on Democracy in a University Research Club 1964 (Box 62)
    - Reflections on Human Nature (Box 62)
    - The Role and Scope of a Faculty Senate (Box 62)
    - Role of the Faculty in University Governance (Box 62)
    - Should Students Participate in University Governance? (Box 62)
    - Some Philosophical Questions about Religion (Box 62)
    - Some Remarks on Disobedient Protest (Box 62)
    - Tenure and Academic Freedom (Box 62)
    - University Neutrality (Box 62)
    - When Good Substance and Good Process Conflict (Box 62)
    - Why Democracy? (Box 62)
    - Will They Bury Us? (Box 62)
  - Books Published
    - Democracy, University of Georgia Press, Athens, 1971; The Free Press, Macmillan, N.Y., 1971 (Box 63)
    - Civil Disobedience: Conscience, Tactics, and the Law, Columbia University Press, N.Y., 1971 (Box 63)
    - Four Systems, Random House, N.Y., 1982 (Box 63)
    - Naked Racial Preference: The Case Against Affirmative Action, Madison Books, Rowman and Littlefield NY, London, 1995 (Box 63)
    - Communism, Fascism and Democracy: The Theoretical Foundations, 3d Edition, McGraw-Hill, N.Y., 1997 (Box 63)
    - The Animal Rights Debate, (with Tom Regan, North Carolina State U.) Rowman & Littlefield, NY, London, 2001 (Box 63)
    - Affirmative Action and Racial Preference, (with James Serba, U. of Notre Dame) Oxford University Press, NY and London, 2003 (Box 63)
    - Essentials of Logic, (with I.M. Copi, Univ. of Hawaii), Prentice-Hall, Upper Saddle River, N.J., 2004 (Box 63)
    - On Rule by the People, (Beijing, The Commercial Press, 2004 (Box 63)
      Chinese translation of DEMOCRACY
    - Introduction to Logic, 12th edition, with Irving M. Copi, Prentice-Hall, New York, London, 2005 (Box 63)
  - Manuscript drafts, galleys, etc
    - Democracy (Box 64)
    - Democracy (Box 65)
    - Democracy (Box 66)
    - Democracy (Box 67)
    - Civil Disobedience (Box 68)
Related Material
The Walter Reuther Library, Wayne State University, Detroit, Mich., has the files of Carl Cohen documenting his work with the American Civil Liberties Union.